Guide to the Wallace Stevens Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Wallace Stevens collection
1921-1966
YCAL MSS 545
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.71
(7 boxes)
The Wallace Stevens collection contains material donated to the library by Wallace Stevens, his daughter Holly Stevens, the Rev. John Curry Gay, and others. The Wallace Stevens gifts include one typed letter signed from Stevens, one manuscript by Stevens, "A Collect of Philosophy," and a bound copy of a score presented to Stevens by Jan Wisse. The Holly Stevens gift consists of a setting draft and galley and page proofs for the Letters of Wallace Stevens (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1966). The Rev. John Curry Gay gift contains writings, letters, and other material, including discarded drafts to poems, most of which appeared in Harmonium (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1923). Materials from other sources include one letter, two drafts, and a publicity photograph.
Stevens, Wallace, 1879-1955
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Wallace Stevens, 1950-1954; Holly Stevens, 1967; Rev. John Curry Gay, 1974; and others.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Wallace Stevens (1978-1955)
Wallace Stevens was an American Modernist poet. He was born in Reading, Pennsylvania, educated at Harvard and then New York Law School, and spent most of his life working as a lawyer for the Hartford insurance company in Connecticut.
Scope and Contents
The Wallace Stevens collection contains material donated to the library by Wallace Stevens, his daughter Holly Stevens, the Rev. John Curry Gay, and others. The Wallace Stevens gifts include one typed letter signed from Stevens, one manuscript by Stevens, "A Collect of Philosophy," and a bound copy of a score presented to Stevens by Jan Wisse. The Holly Stevens gift consists of a setting draft and galley and page proofs for the Letters of Wallace Stevens (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1966). The Rev. John Curry Gay gift contains writings, letters, and other material, including discarded drafts of poems, most of which appeared in Harmonium (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1923). Materials from other sources include one letter, two drafts, and a publicity photograph.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Wallace Stevens Gifts, 1950-1952. II. Holly Stevens Gift, 1966. III. Rev. John Curry Gay Gift, 1921-1926. IV. Material From Other Sources, 1949-1955.
American literature -- 20th Century; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Authors; Gay, John Curry; Stevens, Holly; Stevens, Wallace, 1879-1955; Wisse, Jan, 1921-2008
- Wallace Stevens Gifts, 1950-1952; Series I; 0.21; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Wallace Stevens Gifts consists of three separate small gifts from Stevens, including one typed letter signed from Stevens to Yale University librarian James T. Babb, one manuscript by Stevens, "A Collect of Philosophy," and a bound copy of a score presented to Stevens by Jan Wisse.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gifts of Wallace Stevens, 1950-1954.
  - Letter to James T. Babb, 1950 March 31 (Box 1)
  - "A Collect of Philosophy," drafts, holograph and typescript, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - "Thirteen Ways of Looking at a Blackbird," score, with text by Stevens, 1951-1952 (Box 1)
    With letter from J. Wisse to Stevens, dated 1951
- Holly Stevens Gift, 1966; Series II; 2.09; (5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Series II. Holly Stevens Gift consists of a setting draft and proofs for the Letters of Wallace Stevens (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1966), selected and edited by his daughter Holly Stevens.
  Gift of Holly Stevens, 1967.
  - Letters of Wallace Stevens, setting typsescript, corrected, with proofreaders' marks, 1966; 5 (Box 2)
  - Letters of Wallace Stevens, setting typsescript, corrected, with proofreaders' marks, 1966; 6 (Box 3)
  - Letters of Wallace Stevens, galley proofs, corrected, with printer's annotations, 1966; 2 (Box 4)
  - Letters of Wallace Stevens, page proofs, corrected, 1966; 2 (Box 5)
  - Letters of Wallace Stevens, illustrations, 1966 (Box 6)
  - Letters of Wallace Stevens, miscellaneous pages, 1966 (Box 6)
  - Letters of Wallace Stevens, revised page proofs, corrected, 1966; 4 (Box 6)
  - Letters of Wallace Stevens, revised page proofs, corrected, 1966; 3 (Box 7)
- Rev. John Curry Gay Gift, 1921-1926; Series III; 15
  Organized into three subdivisions for Writings, Correspondence, and Other Material.
  Series III. Rev. John Curry Gay Gift contains writings, letters, and other material. The series features numerous drafts, holograph and typescript, to poems discarded by Stevens while renting an apartment from David Tait Gay and Teresa Curry Gay on 735 Farmington Avenue in West Hartford. Most of the poems found here were published in Harmonium (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1923).
  Gift of Rev. John Curry Gay, 1974.
  - Writings
    - "Anecdote of the Prince of Peacocks", undated (Box 7)
    - "From the Journal of Crispin", [1921 December] (Box 7)
    - "A High-Toned Old Christian Woman", undated (Box 7)
    - "The Jack-Rabbit", undated (Box 7)
    - "Sonatina To Hans Christian", undated (Box 7)
    - "Sunday Morning", undated (Box 7)
    - "Three Travelers Watch a Sunrise", undated (Box 7)
    - "To the One of Fictive Music", undated (Box 7)
    - "Two Figures in Dense Violet Night", undated (Box 7)
    - "The Virgin Carrying a Lantern", undated (Box 7)
    - "The Worms at Heaven's Gate", undated (Box 7)
  - Correspondence
    - Autograph letter signed from Stevens to Mrs. Gay, 1926 December 30 (Box 7)
    - Typed letter signed from The Dial editor Gilbert Seldes to Stevens, 1922 April 26 (Box 7)
  - Other Material
    - Leather billfold, undated (Box 7)
    - Photograph of Holly Stevens, undated (Box 7)
- Material From Other Sources, 1949-1955; Series IV; 5
  Arranged alphabetically by material type and title.
  Series IV. contains material relating to Stevens from other sources. Materials include one letter, two drafts, and a publicity photograph.
  Acquired from various sources, 1950-1975.
  - Letter signed to I. L. Salomon, 1952 April 10 (Box 7)
  - [National Book Award address], 1955 January (Box 7)
  - "An Ordinary Evening in New Haven", 1949, undated (Box 7)
  - Photograph of Wallace Stevens, undated (Box 7)